YINWEI ZHANG

Z zhangyinwei1994@gmail.com · **८** (+1) 520-486-7382 · **in** YINWEI · **%** https://yinwei-zhang.github.io/

Summary

Ph.D. candidate in Industrial Engineering. Masters in Statistics. 1.5 years of industrial experience in developing/deploying deep learning models. Solid theoretical background in machine learning and statistical methods. Proficiency in Python, data science libraries, deep learning frameworks, and SQL. Self-motivated individual with excellent communication and presentation skills.

Education

University of Arizona, United States

Ph.D. Candidate in Industrial Engineering
Master of science in Statistics&Data Science
Master of science in Engineering Management

Aug, 2018 - May, 2023 (Expected) Aug, 2020 - Dec, 2022 (Expected) Aug, 2016 - May, 2018

Jingchu University of Technology, China

Bachelor of science in Process Equipment and Control Engineering

Sep, 2012 - Jul, 2016

Related Coursework: Fundamental of Optimization, Experimental Design, Theory of Probability& Statistics, Statistical Machine Learning, Database Design in SQL, Project Management

Technical Proficiencies

- Soft skills: collaboration, communication, writing, leadership, presentation, quick-learner, data visualization
- Programming skills: Python, R, Matlab, SQL
- Frameworks: TensorFlow, PyTorch, Lua, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, Numpy, Pandas, Git, Linux, Docker, OpenCV
- Awards/Certificates: IEEM Honorable Mention Award, Roots2Resilience Scholarship, AWS Cloud Practitioner (on-going)

Experiences

Research Scientist Intern, ABB Ltd (Fortune 500), Raleigh, NC

Jan, 2020 - Aug, 2021

Highlights: rotated among research groups, went through the life-cycle of deep learning algorithms using PyTorch and TensorFlow

- Developed the pipeline for data preprocessing, model training, testing, and deployment for **image based regression and segmentation** tasks in a **multi-GPU Linux server**. Tools include **TensorFlow/PyTorch**, **TensorFlow Serving**, and **Docker**
- **Fine-tuned** the neural networks with different data fusion mechanisms, learning rate schedulers, optimizers, and backbone layers. Monitored the training and testing processes in **TensorBoard** and prevented overfitting by **early stopping**
- Worked with cross-functional teams to analyze errors of the existing pipeline. Optimized algorithms for data collection, and proposed new algorithms for data augmentation and result interpretations. The overall performance was improved by 30%
- Cooperated with the project managers in identifying the key **evaluation matrics**. **Visualized** and **presented** the results to the technical leaders. The final achievements include **3 patents** and **2 reports**

Research Assistant, University of Arizona

Aug, 2018 - Dec, 2022

Highlights: worked on time series analysis, image processing, and anomaly detection projects using machine learning

- Proposed an **additive regression** method for image-based **anomaly detection** by incorporating **LASSO** and **Ridge** regularizations. Designed a gradient-based optimization algorithm that can run parallely for model estimation with a time complexity $O(n \log n)$ in MATLAB. The F1 score on the testing dataset was improved by 15%
- Developed a simulation pipeline in Docker for studying the failure of the perception system in the autonomous vehicle. Tools include **Python**, **C++**, **ROS**, and **CARLA**. Considered the **temporal correlation** of the failure events and trained a parametric model by **EM algorithm** to predict future failures, improving the MAE by **40**%
- Detected bursts in the water distribution system by **multivariate process monitoring** methods such as MEWMA, MCUSUM, and T-chart in **R**. Trained the models based on the **time-series signals** collected from pipe sensors and determined the optimal parameters by **cross-validation**. Achieved **97% accuracy** in burst detection for the Austin water distribution network
- Proposed an **unsupervised object detection** method by LK optical flow, feature tracking, perspective transformation, and frame differencing using **OpenCV**. Boosted the results by postprocessing such as thresholding, connected component analysis, and morphological operations. The algorithm was transmitted to a Raspberry Pi mounted on an UAV for testing

Hand Disease Diagnosis by Temporal Data Clustering

2022

- Made detailed plans for data collection with repeatable medical experiments. Reduced the data dimensionality and extracted the features of the collected temporal data by the functional **principal component analysis**
- Selected the number of PC by the explained variance and clustered the PC scores via the Gaussian mixture model

Flight Delay Prediction

2022

- Explored and preprocessed the raw tabular data such as filling missing values and creating new features by Pandas
- Constructed a **Random Forest** regressor for delay prediction and searched for optimal parameters with **grid-search**. Interpreted the model by investigating the **feature importance** using **Scikit-learn** and **Matplotlib**

Presentation

- Xia, S., **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J. (2020). Investigation of Curing Process Heterogeneity from Raman Spectrum via CP Decomposition. *INFORMS Annual Meeting*
- **Zhang, Y.** (2019). Tutorial: Applications of Spatial-Temporal Data Analytics in Industry. *Grand Lab Slam Workshop*, University of Arizona, Tucson
- **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J., Lansey, K. (2019). Functional Data Analytics for Detecting Bursts in Water Distribution Systems. *IN-FORMS Annual Meeting*, Seattle
- **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J., Son, Y. (2018). Effective and Efficient Moving Object Detection by a Moving Camera, *INFORMS Annual Meeting*, Phoenix

Publication

- Pan, F., **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J., Head, L., Elli, M., & Alvarez, I. (2022). Quantifying error propagation in multi-stage perception system of autonomous vehicles via physics-based Simulation. *Winter Simulation Conference*, Singapore
- Zhang, Y., Zhang, T., Liu, J., Kang, W., Liang, R., & Potter, B. (2022). Profile extraction for optical lens curing process with Image-based Regularized Tensor Decomposition. *Proceedings of the 2022 International Symposium on Flexible Automation*, Japan
- Nikravesh, Y., **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J., & Frantziskonis, G.N (2022). A partition and microstructure-based method for large-scale topology optimization. *Mechanics of Materials*, Volume 166
- Peterson, R. L., Shea, K. D., Liu, J., Luque, K., Powell, J., **Zhang, Y**., Williams, D. K., Martin-Plank, L., Heasley, B. J., Phillips, L. R., & Crist, J. D. (2021). Family caregiving context: a pilot study. *The Arizona Nurse*, April
- **Zhang, Y.**, Lansey, K., & Liu, J. (2020). Detecting bursts in water distribution system via penalized functional decomposition. IEEM Conference (honorable mention award)
- Lee, S., Jain, S., **Zhang, Y.**, Liu, J., & Son, Y. (2020). A multi-paradigm simulation for the implementation of digital twins in surveillance application. IISE Conference
- Lee, S., Jain, S., Yuan, Y., **Zhang, Y.**, Yang, H., Liu, J., & Son, Y. (2019). Design and development of a DDDAMS-based border surveillance system via UVs and hybrid simulations. *Expert Systems With Applications*, 109-123

Patent

- System and method to generate augmented training data for neural network, No. PCT/US21/37798
- · Robotic systems and methods used with installation of component parts
- Robotic systems and methods used to update training of a neural network based upon neural networks outputs

ර Others

President of INFORMS Student Chapter at the University of Arizona

• Wrote proposals and lead 4 members to hold social events, presentations, and recruiting events for graduate students

Teaching assistant for SIE 506, Quality Engineering

· Assisted students in understanding process monitoring methods such as hypothesis testing, CUSUM, and EWMA

Teaching assistant for SIE 533, Fundamentals of Data Science for Engineers

• Demonstrated the logistic regression, boosting, and decision tree using Python, Numpy, Pandas, and Scikit-learn